<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1982 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1982.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4387 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4387.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6480 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6480.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6481 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6481.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6488 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6488.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6489 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6489.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7942 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8182 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8182.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8630 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8630.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8488 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8488.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9286 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9286.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std"
docName="draft-ietf-sidrops-manifest-numbers-01"
ipr="trust200902" updates="RFC9286" consensus="true">

  <front>
    <title>RPKI Manifest Number Handling</title>

    <author initials="T." surname="Harrison" fullname="Tom Harrison">
        <organization abbrev="APNIC">Asia Pacific Network Information Centre</organization>
        <address>
            <postal>
                <street>6 Cordelia St</street>
                <city>South Brisbane</city>
                <code>4101</code>
                <country>Australia</country>
                <region>QLD</region>
            </postal>
            <email>tomh@apnic.net</email>
        </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George G. Michaelson" initials="G." surname="Michaelson">
	<organization abbrev="APNIC">Asia-Pacific Network Information Centre</organization>

	<address>
	    <postal>
		<street>6 Cordelia St</street>
		<city>South Brisbane</city>
		<region>QLD</region>
		<code>4101</code>
		<country>Australia</country>
	    </postal>
	    <email>ggm@apnic.net</email>
	</address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
	<organization>Fastly</organization>
	<address>
	    <postal>
		<street/>
		<city>Amsterdam</city>
		<region/>
		<country>Netherlands</country>
	    </postal>
	    <email>job@fastly.com</email>
	</address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>template</keyword>
    <abstract>
        <t>

            The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) makes use of
            signed objects called manifests.  A manifest lists each
            file that a publisher intends to include within an RPKI
            repository, and can be used to detect certain forms of
            attack against a repository.  Manifests include a
            "manifest number" (manifestNumber), which the publisher
            must increment whenever it issues a new manifest, and
            Relying Parties (RPs) are required to verify that a
            newly-retrieved manifest for a given Certification
            Authority (CA) has a higher manifestNumber than the
            previously-validated manifest.  However, the
            manifestNumber field is 20 octets in length (i.e. not
            unbounded), and no behaviour is specified for when a
            manifestNumber reaches the largest possible value.  This
            document specifies publisher and RP behaviour for this
            scenario.

        </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>

            The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) <xref
            target="RFC6480" /> makes use of signed objects <xref
            target="RFC6488" /> called manifests <xref
            target="RFC9286" />.  A manifest lists each file that a
            publisher intends to include within an RPKI repository
            <xref target="RFC6481" />, and can be used to detect
            certain forms of attack against a repository.  Manifests
            include a "manifest number" (manifestNumber), which the
            publisher must increment whenever it issues a new
            manifest, and Relying Parties (RPs) are required to verify
            that a newly-retrieved manifest for a given Certification
            Authority (CA) has a higher manifestNumber than the
            previously-validated manifest (see section 4.2.1 of <xref
            target="RFC9286" />).

        </t>

        <t>

            However, the manifestNumber field is 20 octets in length
            (i.e. not unbounded), and no behaviour is specified for
            when a manifestNumber reaches the largest possible value
            (2^159-1), which means that a publisher can no longer make
            use of a given CA certificate when that value is reached.
            (For the purposes of <xref target="RFC9286" />, a "CA" is
            represented by a CA certificate with a stable location and a
            stable private key. Reissuing a CA certificate with changed
            resources or a changed expiry date does not change the
            identity of the CA such that the stored manifestNumber for
            the CA is reset, for example.)

        </t>

        <t>

            While it is practically impossible for a publisher to
            reach the largest possible value under normal operating
            conditions (it would require that the publisher issue one
            manifest per second for 23,171,956,451,847,141,650,870
            quintillion years), there is a chance that it could be
            reached due to bugs in the issuance or publication systems
            or incorrect/inadvertent use of those systems.  For
            example:

            occur:

            <list>

                <t>Incrementing by large values when issuing
                manifests, such that the time to reach that largest
                value is reduced.</t>

                <t>Reissuing new manifests in an infinite delay-free
                loop, such that the manifestNumber increases by a
                large value in a comparatively short period of
                time.</t>

                <t>Inadvertently setting the manifestNumber to the
                largest possible value, such that the publisher will
                no longer be able to publish usable manifests for that
                repository.</t>

            </list>

            These scenarios might also arise in combination and be
            more severe as a result: for example, a large manifest
            number increment bug in conjunction with a manifest
            reissuance loop problem.

        </t>

        <t>

            For a subordinate CA, the risk of repository invalidation
            due to this problem can be addressed by the publisher
            simply using the key rollover process (<xref
            target="RFC6489" />) to get a new Certification Authority
            (CA) certificate.  RPs will treat this new certificate as
            though it represents a distinct CA, and the manifestNumber
            can be reset at that point.

        </t>

        <t>

            However, this option is not available for RPKI Trust
            Anchors (TAs).  If a TA publishes a manifest with the
            largest-possible manifestNumber value, then it is not
            possible to make use of the TA after that point, because
            the certificate location (stored in the associated Trust
            Anchor Locator (TAL) <xref target="RFC8630" />) and its
            private key cannot be changed.  Issuing a new TA and
            distributing the associated TAL to clients would involve a
            large amount of work for TA operators and RPs, and there
            would be a limited degree of RPKI protection by way of
            that TA for the time between the issuance of the
            problematic manifest and the installation of the new TAL
            for a given client.

        </t>

        <t>

            In order to avoid these problems, this document defines
            how publishers and RPs can handle this scenario in order
            to facilitate ongoing use of an affected repository.

        </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119" /> <xref target="RFC8174"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="manifest-number-handling" title="Manifest Number Handling">

        <t>

            For a given CA, an RP MUST NOT reject a new manifest
            issued by that CA on the grounds of it not having a higher
            manifestNumber than a previously-validated manifest if the
            new manifest has a different filename from that of the
            previously-validated manifest.  In other words, an RP MUST
            reset its stored manifestNumber for a given CA if the CA
            changes the filename of its manifest.

        </t>

        <t>

            With this behaviour, it is possible for a CA to be
            configured such that any time it issues a new manifest, it
            uses a new filename for that manifest.  If a CA were
            configured in this way, the manifestNumber validation set
            out in section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC9286" /> would
            have no purpose.  To avoid this outcome, CAs SHOULD NOT
            use new filenames for manifests except in situations where
            it is necessary to ensure the ongoing validity of the CA
            or its repository.  Similarly, RP software SHOULD alert
            its operators when a manifest filename changes for a given
            CA.

        </t>

        <t>

            To avoid certain forms of replay attack, the RP MUST
            verify that the URI in the accessLocation in one of the
            id-ad-signedObject accessMethods in the manifest's Subject
            Information Access (SIA) extension exactly matches the URI
            presented in the RPKI Repository Delta Protocol (RRDP)
            <xref target="RFC8182" /> "publish" element or the URI
            accessed on the remote rsync source server.

        </t>

        <t>

            Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC6481" /> contains
            non-normative guidance for the naming of manifest files in
            repositories.  While a CA that supports the behaviour described
            in this section cannot preserve the exact filename
            suggested by that text (per section 2.1 of <xref
            target="RFC4387" />), the CA SHOULD still ensure that the
            filename is a value derived from the public key of the CA,
            per the more general guidance in that section.

        </t>

        <t>

            Note that the approach set out in this section is
            different from that described in <xref target="RFC8488"
            section="3.2.1"/>.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="general-repository-handling" title="General Repository Handling">

        <t>

            The previous section contains a specific update for the
            handling of manifest numbers, in order to address one
            potential permanent invalidity scenario.  RPs that
            encounter other permanent invalidity scenarios SHOULD also
            consider how those can be addressed such that the scenario
            does not require the relevant CA or TA to perform a key
            rollover operation.  For example, in the event that an RP
            recognises that a permanent invalidity scenario has
            occurred, the RP could alert the operator and provide an
            option to the operator to stop relying on cached data for
            the affected repository, so that the CA can rectify the
            problem.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations">

        <t>

            CA software may opt to support the manifest number reset
            functionality in various ways.  For example, it could
            change the manifest filename when the manifestNumber
            reaches a certain threshold, or it could alert the
            operator in this scenario and request confirmation that
            the filename should be changed.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>

            N/A

        </t>
    </section>

    <section removeInRFC="true">
      <name>Implementation status</name>
      <t>
        This section records the status of known implementations of the protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref target="RFC7942" />.
        The description of implementations in this section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing drafts to RFCs.
        Please note that the listing of any individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
        Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors.
        This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their features.
        Readers are advised to note that other implementations may exist.
      </t>
      <t>
        According to <xref target="RFC7942" />, "this will allow reviewers and working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols more mature.
        It is up to the individual working groups to use this information as they see fit".
      </t>

      <ul>
        <li>
          OpenBSD <xref target="rpki-client"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>
            The authors would like to thank
            <contact fullname="Theo Buehler"/>
            for their review and feedback on this document.
        </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC4387;
      &RFC6488;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC8182;
      &RFC9286;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1982;
      &RFC5280;
      &RFC6480;
      &RFC6481;
      &RFC6489;
      &RFC7942;
      &RFC8630;
      &RFC8488;
      <reference anchor="rpki-client" target="https://www.rpki-client.org/">
        <front>
          <title>rpki-client</title>
            <author>
            <organization>OpenBSD Project</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2024" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Serial Number Arithmetic">

        <t>

            Serial number arithmetic <xref target="RFC1982" /> is an
            approach that has been used in the DNS context (among
            others) to permit the indefinite use of a finite number
            space.  At least in theory, it would be possible to use a
            similar approach with the manifestNumber field as well.

        </t>

        <t>

            However, unlike the corresponding DNS context with Start
            of Authority (SOA) resource records, an RPKI CA does not
            have visibility into or control over RPKI RPs generally.
            This means that it is not possible to select an updated
            manifestNumber value or to manage the relevant state
            transitions so as to guarantee that all RPs will have
            valid state at the end of the process.  The approach
            proposed in <xref target="manifest-number-handling" />
            does not have this problem.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Manifest thisUpdate">

        <t>

            The thisUpdate field in the manifest object is of type
            GeneralizedTime, defined in section 4.1.2.5.2 of <xref
            target="RFC5280" />.  This type has a maximum value of
            99991231235959Z (i.e. 31 December 9999 23:59:59 GMT).
            Section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC9286" /> requires that
            "[e]ach RP MUST verify that this field value is greater
            (more recent) than the most recent manifest it has
            validated", so it would appear to be subject to the same
            problem as for manifest numbers.  However, during
            validation, if the RP detects that the current time is not
            between the manifest thisUpdate and nextUpdate values, the
            RP must treat the fetch as a failed fetch.  Therefore, the
            RP will not cache a manifest with a current date far in
            the future, and the CA can rectify the problem here by
            reissuing the relevant manifest with the correct date.

        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="walkthrough">
      <name>Walkthrough of the rpki-client implementation</name>
      <t>
	This section describes the <xref target="rpki-client"/> implementation
	with regard to handling manifest numbers. The process is composed of
        multiple stages:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li>Fetching the manifests and acquiring referenced files</li>
        <li>Preprocessing of the manifests</li>
        <li>Selecting the first candidate manifest</li>
        <li>Matching file names and hashes</li>
        <li>Optionally selecting the second candidate manifest</li>
      </ol>

     <section anchor="s1" toc="exclude">
       <name>Stage: Fetching the Manifests and Acquiring Referenced Files</name>
       <t>
	 The RP follows <em>rpkiNotify</em> or <em>caRepository</em> pointers
	 in the <em>SubjectInfoAccess</em> extension of valid CA certificates
         to queue up synchronization tasks.
       </t>
       <t>
	 At the end of this stage the RP has zero, one, or two manifests for a
	 given <em>caRepository</em>. Depending on the validation status, the
	 RP stores files into two locations: <em>DIR_VALID</em> or
	 <em>DIR_TEMP</em>. <em>DIR_VALID</em> contains objects which were
         found to be valid (current, not revoked, not expired) during the previous
	 validation run, the <em>DIR_TEMP</em> location contains files
	 retrieved via RRDP or rsync which have not yet been validated, or were
         rejected by the validation process.
       </t>
       <t>
	 If the remote publication point is unreachable on both RRDP and rsync,
	 no purported "new" manifest file will be stored in <em>DIR_TEMP</em>.
	 It is possible that the <em>DIR_VALID</em> location contains a locally
         cached version of the object from a previous validation run.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section anchor="s2" toc="exclude">
       <name>Stage: preprocessing of the manifests</name>
       <t>
	 Constructing the path and filename based on the <em>rpkiManifest</em>
	 of the CA certificate, the RP attempts to open what purportedly are
	 two version of the same <em>.mft</em> file in <em>DIR_TEMP</em> and
         <em>DIR_VALID</em>, respectively.
       </t>
       <t>
	 For brevity's sake, the version in <em>DIR_TEMP</em> is associated
	 with a data structure named <strong>mft1</strong>, the version in
         <em>DIR_VALID</em> is associated with a data structure named
         <strong>mft2</strong>.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Assuming two files exist in the <em>DIR_TEMP</em> and
	 <em>DIR_VALID</em> locations, both files are run through a series of
	 checks. If any check fails, that file will be considered ineligible.
       </t>
       <ol>
         <li>Can the file be opened?</li>
         <li>Can the content of the file be decoded as DER?</li>
         <li>Can the DER-content be parsed as CMS ContentInfo?</li>
         <li>Is the CMS self-signage correct?</li>
         <li>Can exactly one CMS SignerInfo be extracted?</li>
         <li>Is the ContentInfo of the right version?</li>
         <li>Is the SignerInfo of the right version?</li>
         <li>Does the SignerInfo have the correct signed attributes?</li>
         <li>Does the SignerInfo have the correct digest and signature algorithms?</li>
         <li>Does the ContentInfo have the right type of embedded content?</li>
         <li>Does the eContentType match the Content-Type?</li>
         <li>Does the CMS contain zero CRLs?</li>
         <li>Can exactly one X.509 cert be extracted from the SignerInfo?</li>
         <li>Can the notBefore field be extracted from the X.509 cert?</li>
         <li>Can the notAfter field be extracted from the X.509 cert?</li>
         <li>Does the X.509 cert's SKI match the SignerInfo's SignerIdentifier?</li>
         <li>Can the AIA be extracted from the X.509 EE?</li>
         <li>Can the AKI be extracted from the X.509 EE?</li>
         <li>Can the SIA be extracted from the X.509 EE?</li>
         <li>Does the SIA Signed Object pathname match the pathname presented by the publication point?</li>
         <li>Can the SKI be extracted from the X.509 EE?</li>
         <li>Are the X509 EE's RFC 3779 extensions set to inherit?</li>
         <li>Can the eContent be parsed according to the ASN.1 formal syntax?</li>
         <li>Is the Manifest eContent of the right version?</li>
         <li>Can the manifestNumber be extracted?</li>
         <li>Is the CMS signing-time before the Manifest nextUpdate time?</li>
         <li>Is 'now' not before the Manifest thisUpdate?</li>
         <li>Is 'now' not after the Manifest nextUpdate?</li>
         <li>Is the Manifest nextUpdate not before the Manifest thisUpdate?</li>
         <li>Does a valid certification path from a TA to this EE cert exist?</li>
       </ol>
       <t>
	  Through the above checks, the <strong>mft1</strong> and
	  <strong>mft2</strong> data structures are populated, or marked
          ineligible.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="s3" toc="exclude">
        <name>Stage: selecting the first candidate manifest</name>
        <t>
	  Assuming both <strong>mft1</strong> and <strong>mft2</strong>
	  successfully passed through <xref target="s2">stage 2</xref>, a
	  comparison can be made between <strong>mft1</strong> and
          <strong>mft2</strong> to select the candidate mft for the next stage.
        </t>
        <t>
	  The RP checks whether the locally cached version
	  <strong>mft2</strong> (from <em>DIR_VALID</em>) is older in the sense
	  that was issued earlier than <strong>mft1</strong> (from
	  <em>DIR_TEMP</em>) by comparing the Manifest <em>thisUpdate</em>
	  timestamp, and has a smaller <em>manifestNumber</em>. If both
	  conditions are true, the RP will select <strong>mft1</strong> as
          candidate for stage <xref target="s4">stage 4</xref>. 
        </t>
        <t>
	  If there was some kind of issue with <strong>mft1</strong>(such as it
	  being older than or has the same <em>thisUpdate</em> as
	  <strong>mft2</strong>, or it having a <em>manifestNumber</em> which
	  is lower than or equal to <strong>mft2</strong>), the RP proceeds
          with <xref target="s5">stage 5</xref>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="s4" toc="exclude">
        <name>Stage: matching file names and hashes for mft1</name>
        <t>
	  The RP will now verify the hash value of each file listed in manifest
	  <strong>mft1</strong> matches the value obtained by hashing the file
	  acquired from the publication point. If the computed hash value of a
	  file listed on the manifest does not match the hash value contained
	  in the manifest, then a <em>failed fetch</em> occurred and the RP
          proceeds to <xref target="s5">stage 5</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
	  If all the files and hashes matched, <strong>mft1</strong> and its
          associated files are moved from <em>DIR_TEMP</em> to
          <em>DIR_VALID</em>. The manifest handling procedure now ends.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="s5" toc="exclude">
        <name>Optional Stage: matching file names and hashes for mft2</name>
        <t>
          This stage is only reached if there was an issue with <strong>mft1</strong>.
        </t>
        <t>
	  The RP will now verify the hash value of each file listed in manifest
	  <strong>mft2</strong> matches the value obtained by hashing the file
	  acquired from the publication point. If the computed hash value of a
	  file listed on the manifest does not match the hash value contained
          in the manifest, then the <em>caRepository</em> is busted.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
